<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fortunate farevvel to the most forward and noble Earle of Essex, one of the honorable priuie counsel, Earle high Marshal of England, Master of the horse, Master of the ordinance, Knight of the garter, &amp; Lord Lieutenant general of all the Queenes Maiesties forces in Ireland Dedicated to the right Honorable the Lord Harry Seamer, second sonne to the last Duke of Sommerset. Written by Thomas Churchyard Esquire.</title>
            <author>Churchyard, Thomas, 1520?-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5234</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840743</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5272</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5272)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 192:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fortunate farevvel to the most forward and noble Earle of Essex, one of the honorable priuie counsel, Earle high Marshal of England, Master of the horse, Master of the ordinance, Knight of the garter, &amp; Lord Lieutenant general of all the Queenes Maiesties forces in Ireland Dedicated to the right Honorable the Lord Harry Seamer, second sonne to the last Duke of Sommerset. Written by Thomas Churchyard Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Churchyard, Thomas, 1520?-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edm. Bollifant, for William Wood at the west doore of Powles,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The fortunate farewell to the noble Earle of Essex.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1566-1601 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5272:1"/>
            <p>THE FORTVNATE FAREWE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the moſt forward and noble Earle of Eſſex, one of the honorable priuie Counſel, Earle high Marſhal of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Maſter of the horſe, Maſter of the ordinance, Knight of the garter, &amp; Lord Lieutenant general of all the Queenes Maieſties forces in Ireland.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to the right Honorable the Lord HARRY SEAMER, ſecond ſonne to the laſt Duke of Sommerſet.</p>
            <p>Written by Thomas Churchyard Eſquire.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by Edm. Bollifant, for William Wood at the weſt doore of Powles. 1599</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5272:2"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Thomas Churchyard</hi> wiſheth continuance of vertue, bleſſedneſſe of minde, and wiſhed felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N all duty (my good Lord) I am bold, becauſe your moſt honorable father the Duke of Sommerſet (vncle to the renowmed impe of grace noble <hi>King Edward</hi> the ſixt) fauoured me when I was troubled before the Lords of the Counſell, for writing ſome of my firſt verſes: in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uit all whereof euer ſince I haue honored all his noble race, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your Lordſhip in ſea ſeruices forward and ready in all honorable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ner (ſparing for no charges) when the Spanyards approched neere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>countrie, I bethought me how I might be thankfull for good turnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of your noble progente, though vnable therefore finding my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e vnfurniſhed of all things woorthy preſentation and acceptance, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke occaſion of the departure of a most woorthy Earle towardes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uice in Ireland, ſo made a preſent to your Lordſhip of his happy Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll as I hope: and truſt to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue and ſee his wiſhed welcome home. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rewell onely deuiſed to ſtirre vp a threefold manly courage to the reenarie multitude of ſold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, that follow this Marſhall like Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, and eſpecially to mooue all degrees in generall loyally to ſerue our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and valiantly to go through with good reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion the acceptable ſeruice they take in hand. Which true ſeruice ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>louble their renowne, and enroll their names in the memoriall booke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fame for euer. I feare I leade your Lordſhip too farre with the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of a fruitleſſe pen, whoſe blandiſhing phraſe makes many to gaze <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and few to conſider well of and regarde. My plot is onely l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ude to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chaſe good will of vertuous people, what the reſt thinke, let their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſconſtruing conceires anſwere their owne idle humors. This plaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſent winning your Lordſhips good liking, ſhall paſſe with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grace to his honorable hands, that the praiers &amp; power of good men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ites willingly vpon towards the reformation of wicked rebellion.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll at commandement,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Thoma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Churchyard.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5272:2"/>
            <head>The happy Farewell to the fortunate and forward moſt noble Earle of Eſſex.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw SCIPIO ſails, to Affrick far from hoem</l>
               <l>The Lord of hoeſts, and battels be his gied,</l>
               <l>Now when green trees, begins to bud and bloem,</l>
               <l>On Iriſh ſeas, ELIZAS ſhips ſhall ried,</l>
               <l>A warliek band, of worthy knights I hoep,</l>
               <l>Aer armd for fight, a bloedy brunt to bied,</l>
               <l>With rebels ſhall, boeth might and manhoed coep</l>
               <l>Our contreis right, and quarrell to be tried:</l>
               <l>Right maeks wrong bluſh, and troeth bids falſhed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>The ſword is drawn, TYROENS diſpatch draws ny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A traitor muſt, be taught to know his king,</l>
               <l>When MARS ſhal march, with ſhining ſword in ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>A crauen cock, cries creak and hangs down wing,</l>
               <l>Will run about, the ſhraep and daer not ſtand,</l>
               <l>When cocks of gaem, coms in to giue a bloe,</l>
               <l>So falſe TYROEN, may faint when he would fight,</l>
               <l>Thogh now alowd, on dunghill doth he croe,</l>
               <l>Traitors wants hart, and often taeks the flight:</l>
               <l>When rebels ſee, they aer ſurprieſd by troeth,</l>
               <l>Pack hence in haeſt, away the rebels goeth.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5272:3"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oud trecherous traſh, is curbd &amp; knockt with bloes,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> loftie mindes, with force are beaten down,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainſt the right, though oft rued rebels roes,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t oen ſped well, that did impeach a crowne.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad the Annaels, of all the Princes paſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hear treaſons ſtill, are puniſht in their kinde,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear ſhall you ſee, when faithfull men ſtand faſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe traytors ſtill, are but a blaſt of winde:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rhe that firſt, formd kings and all degrees,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ruel of ſtaets, and kingdoms ouerſees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t and rage, this rank rebellion breeds,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ock and ſpoyl, ſets bloudſhed ſo abroetch,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ethles attempts, their filthy humor feeds,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hnes runs on, all hedlong to reproetch:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dnes begaet, theas helhounds all a roe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſons of ſhaem, and childern of Gods wraeth,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th woluiſh minds, liek breetchles beares they goe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow woods and bogs, and many a crooked paeth:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng liek dogs, in litter, dung and ſtrawe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed as bruet beaſts, that knoes ne ruel nor lawe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5272:3"/>
               <l>Foſtred from faith, and fear of God or man,</l>
               <l>Vnlernd or taught, of any graces good,</l>
               <l>Nurſt vp in vice, whear falſe hed firſt began,</l>
               <l>Mercyles boern, ſtill ſheading giltles blood.</l>
               <l>Libertiens lewd, that all good order haets,</l>
               <l>Murtherers viel, of wemen great with childe,</l>
               <l>Cruell as kiets, deſpiſing all eſtaets,</l>
               <l>Diuliſhly bent, boeth curriſh, ſtern and wilde:</l>
               <l>Their whoel deuice, is rooet of miſcheeues all,</l>
               <l>That ſeeks a plaeg, on their own heds to fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Will God permit, ſuch monſters to beare ſway,</l>
               <l>His iuſtice haets, the ſteps of tyrants ſtill,</l>
               <l>Their damnable deeds, craues vengeance euery day</l>
               <l>Which God doth ſcourge, by his own bleſſed will,</l>
               <l>He planteth force, to fling down feeble ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Men of mutch worth, to weaken things of noght,</l>
               <l>Whoes cloked craft, ſhall ſuer be ſeen at length,</l>
               <l>When vnto light, dark dealings ſhall be broght:</l>
               <l>Sweet ciuill Lords, ſhall ſawſy fellowes meet,</l>
               <l>Who muſt ask grace, on knees at honors feet.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5272:4"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uednes may range, a while in ruffling ſort,</l>
               <l>As witleſſe wights, with wandring maeks world mues</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut when powre coms, to cut prowd practiſe ſhort,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſhoe by ſword, how ſubiects Prince abues,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen conſhens ſhall, Peccaui cry in feeld,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>remble and quaek, mutch liek an Aſpin leaf,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut when on knees, do conquerd captiues yeeld,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he victor turns, his hed as he wear deaf:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueth is grown cold, reuenge is hot as fier,</l>
               <l>And mercy ſits, with frowns in angry attier.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>World paſt forgaue, great faults and let them pas,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime preſent loeks, on futuer time to com,</l>
               <l>All aegis ſawe, their follies in a glas,</l>
               <l>Yet were not taught, by time nor ſound of drom,</l>
               <l>This world groes blinde, and neither ſees nor heers,</l>
               <l>Their ſenſes fail, the wits and reaſon faints,</l>
               <l>Old world is waxt, worm eaten by long yeers,</l>
               <l>And men becom, black diuels that were ſaints:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et Gods great grace, this wretched caus reforms,</l>
               <l>And from fayr flowrs, weeds out the wicked worms.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5272:4"/>
               <l>They com that ſhall, redreſſe great things amis,</l>
               <l>Pluck vp the weeds, plant roſes in their place,</l>
               <l>No violent thing, enduers long as hit is,</l>
               <l>Falſehed flies faſt, from ſight of true mens face,</l>
               <l>Traitors do fear, the plaegs for them prepard,</l>
               <l>And hieds their heds, in hoels when troeth is ſeen,</l>
               <l>Thogh graceleſſe giues, to duty ſmall regard,</l>
               <l>Good ſubiects yeelds, obedience to their Queen:</l>
               <l>In quarrels iuſt, do thouſands offer liues,</l>
               <l>They feel fowl bobs, that for the bucklars ſtriues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Lord doth bring, for ſtrength the fear of God,</l>
               <l>The loue of men, and ſword of iuſtice boeth,</l>
               <l>Which three is to, TYROEN an iron rod,</l>
               <l>A birtchin twig, that draws bloed whear hit goeth,</l>
               <l>When IOAB went, to warr in DAVIDS right,</l>
               <l>He broght hoem peace, in ſpite of emnies beard,</l>
               <l>For IOZIAS, the Lord aboue did fight,</l>
               <l>With Angels force, that maed the foes afeard:</l>
               <l>The world doth ſhaek, and tremble at his frown,</l>
               <l>Whoes beck ſoon caſts, the brags of rebels down.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5272:5"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and faſt and ſuer, falſe traitors turns their back,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rue ſubiects veaw, maeks haerbrain rebels bluſh,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tout heauy bloes, maeks higheſt trees to crack,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n armed piek, may brauely bied a puſh,</l>
               <l>Wheel not about, ſtand ſtiffe liek brazen wall,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or thats the way, to win the feeld in deed,</l>
               <l>Charge the foer front, and ſee the emnies fall,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he cowards brag, is but a rotten reed:</l>
               <l>Victors muſt beare, the brunt of eury ſhock,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſtant minde, is liek a ſtony rock.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arewell ſweet Lords, Knights, Captains and the reſt,</l>
               <l>Who goes with you, taeks threefold thankfull pain,</l>
               <l>Who ſets you forth, is ten times treble bleſt,</l>
               <l>Who ſerues you well, reaps glory for their gain,</l>
               <l>Who dies ſhall liue, in faem among the beſt,</l>
               <l>Who liues ſhall loek, and laugh theas broils to ſcorn,</l>
               <l>All honeſt harts, doth ciuill warr deteſt,</l>
               <l>And curſe the time, that ear TYROEN was born:</l>
               <l>We hoep good hap, waits on the fleet that goes,</l>
               <l>And Gods great help, ſhall clean deſtroy our foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5272:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
